Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
“让我们举杯，祝福那些
将他们的思想镶嵌在
重重括号之间的Lisp程序员。”
翻译&&时间轴
杨启钊
（windfarer）
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
存储分配与垃圾收集
PROFESSOR: Well, there's one bit of mystery left,
教授: 接下来我要解开
which I'd like to get rid of right now.
目前仅剩的谜团
And that's that we've been blithely doing things like cons
我们能毫无顾虑地进行CONS
assuming there's always another one.
就好像空间足够多一样
That we've been doing these things like
我们总是在使用
car-ing and cdr-ing
CAR和CDR
and assuming that we had some idea
并假设知道我们知道
how this can be done.
它们是如何实现的
Now indeed
事实上
we said that that's equivalent to having procedures.
我们认为它们是基本过程
OK? But that doesn't really solve the problem,
但这没有真正解决问题
because the procedure need all sorts of complicated mechanisms
因为过程依赖各种复杂的机制
like environment structures
需要诸如环境结构之类的东西
and things like that to work.
才能运行起来
And those were ultimately made out of conses
而归根结底它们也是
in the model that we had,
由CONS之类的东西构成的
so that really doesn't solve the problem.
这的确没有解决问题
Now the problem here is
目前的问题是
is the glue the data structure's made out of.
粘合这些数据结构的是什么东西？
What kind of possible thing could it be?
它可能是怎样的一个东西?
OK? We've been showing you things like a machine,
我们已经见过了一台机器
a computer that has a controller,
一台计算机具有一个控制器
and some registers,
和一些寄存器
and maybe a stack.
还可能有一个栈
And we haven't said anything about,
但是我们还没提到一些东西
for example, larger memory.
例如 大内存
And I think that's what we have to worry about right now.
我想 现在是时候讨论它们了
But just to make it perfectly clear
但是先要说清楚
that this is an inessential,
这个并不是必须的
purely implementational thing,
只是一些实现上的细节
I'd like to show you, for example,
让我举个例子
how you can do it all with the numbers.
如何用数字来表示这些东西
That's an easy one.
有个比较简单的方法
Famous fellow by the name of Godel,
一位著名的逻辑学家 哥德尔
a logician at the end of the 1930s,
在20世纪30年代末
invented a very clever way
发明了一个很巧妙的方法
of encoding the complicated expressions
能够把复杂的表达式
as numbers.
表示成数字
For example--
例如
I'm not saying exactly what Godel's scheme is,
我不会照搬哥德尔的方法
because he didn't use words like cons.
因为他没有使用CONS之类的术语
He had other kinds of
他使用了其它的组合手段
of ways of combining to make expressions.
来编码表达式
But he said,
他的思路是
I'm going to assign a number to every algebraic expression.
用不同数字分别代表每个代数式
And the way I'm going to manufacture these numbers
通过组合各个部分的数字
is by combining the numbers of the parts.
来形成新的表达式
So for example,
举例来说
what we were doing our world,
我们在创造世界的时候
we could say that if objects
如果用数字
are represented by numbers,
来表示对象
then cons of x and y
那么(CONS X Y)
could be represented by,
就可以表示为
2 to the x times 3 to the y.
2^X * 3^Y
Because then we could extract the parts.
因为这样我们还能取出它的每一部分
We could say, for example,
举例来说
that then car of, say, x
(CAR X)
is the number of factors of 2 in x.
就是X中因数2的个数
OK? And of course cdr is the same thing.
当然(CDR X)是一样的
It's the number of factors of 3 in x.
它就X中因数3的个数
Now this is a perfectly reasonable scheme,
这是个非常合理的方案
except for the fact that
只不过就是
the numbers rapidly get to be much larger
数字的位数
in number of digits
会急剧地增大
than the number of protons in the universe.
甚至比宇宙中的粒子还多
So there's no easy way to use this scheme
所以除了在理论中
other than the theoretical one.
没有实现这种方案的好办法
On the other hand,
另一方面
there are other ways of representing these things.
也有其它的表示方式
We have been thinking in terms
我们把它们表示为
of little boxes, boxes.
一些小盒子
We've been thinking about our cons structures
我们把CONS结构
as looking sort of like this.
想象为这样的东西
They're little pigeon holes with things in them.
它们是里面装着东西的小隔间
And of course we arrange them in little trees.
这些格子组成一个树
I wish that the semiconductor manufacturers
我希望半导体制造商
would supply me with something appropriate for this,
能够提供适配这样需求的芯片
but actually
但事实上
what they do supply me with
他们提供给我的却是
is a linear memory.
线性的内存
Memory is sort of a big pile of pigeonholes,
内存是一串小隔间
pigeonholes like this.
像这样的小隔间
Each of which can hold a certain sized object,
每个小隔间里可以保存确定大小的对象
a fixed size object.
一个尺寸固定的对象
So, for example,
例如
a complicated list with 25 elements
一个含25个元素的表
won't fit in one of these.
就放不进这里
However, each of these
然而 它们中的每一个
is indexed by an address.
都是由地址索引的
So the address might be
因此它们的地址可能是
zero here,
这里是0
one here,
这里是1
two here,
这里是2
three here,
这里是3
and so on.
以此类推
That we write these down as numbers is unimportant.
这里写的数字并不重要
What matters is that they're distinct
重要的是 它们不重复
as a way to get to the next one.
有了它们就能找到下一个在哪
And inside of each of these,
在其中每一个小隔间里面
we can stuff something into these pigeonholes.
我们可以把东西放进去
That's what memory is like,
对于没有造过计算机的我们来说
for those of you who haven't built a computer.
内存就是这样子的
Now.
现在
Now the problem is
现在的问题是
how are we going to impose on this type of structure,
如何用这样的结构
this nice tree structure.
来实现这个树形结构
Well it's not very hard,
其实并不难
and there have been numerous schemes involved in this.
已经有大量的方案来做这个了
The most important one is to say,
最重要的一个方案是
well assuming that the semiconductor manufacturer
假设半导体制造商
allows me to arrange my memory
允许我安排自己的内存
so that one of these pigeonholes is big enough
使得其中每个小隔间都足够大
to hold the address of another
能够装得下另一个的地址
OK. I have been made.
我需要这么来安排
Now it actually has to be a little bit bigger
事实上它需要更大一点
because I have to also install or store some information
因为我还要在里面存放一些信息
as to a tag which describes the kind of thing that's there.
它标示了这里面是什么东西
And we'll see that in a second.
我们过一会就能看到
And of course if the semiconductor manufacturer
当然 如果半导体制造商
doesn't arrange it so I can do that,
没有这么来制造
then of course I can, with some cleverness,
我就需要用一些机智的方式
arrange combinations of these to fit together in that way.
把它们组合起来以供使用
So we're going to have to imagine
我们想象一下
imposing this complicated tree structure
把这个复杂的树形结构
on our nice linear memory.
塞进线性内存里
If we look at the first still store,
我们来看第一张幻灯片
we see a classic scheme for doing that.
可以看到一个传统的实现方案
It's a standard way of representing list structures
它是把表结构放入线性内存
in a linear memory.
的标准方式
What we do is we divide this memory
我们把这块内存
into two parts.
分为两部分
An array called the cars,
一个叫THE-CARS的数组
and an array called the cdrs.
一个叫THE-CDRS的数组
Now whether those happen to be
无论它们是
sequential addresses or whatever,
顺序的地址或是其它的
it's not important.
其实并不重要
That's somebody's implementation details.
这是实现细节了
But there are two arrays here.
但有两个数组
Linear arrays indexed
线性数组是由
by sequential indices like this.
顺序的下标索引的
What is stored in each of these pigeonholes
每个小格子里存的
is a typed object.
是一个带类型的对象
And what we have here
这里的类型
are types which begin with letters like p,
以字母P开头
standing for a pair.
表示序对
Or n, standing for a number.
以N开头 表示数字
Or e, standing for an empty list.
E开头 表示空表
The end of the list.
也就是表尾标志
And so if we wish to represent
如果我们想表示
an object like this,
这样一个对象
the list beginning with 1, 2
首元素为(1 2)
and then having a 3 and a 4
然后3、4分别作为
and then having a 3 and a 4 as its second and third elements.
它的第二和第三个元素
A list containing a list as its first part
这个表的第一部分也是一个表
and then two numbers
后面接着是两个数字
as a second and third parts.
分别为第二和第三部分
Then of course we draw it sort of like this these days,
现在我们用盒子-指针表示法
in box-and-pointer notation.
来描绘它
And you see,
你能发现
these are the three cells
这里有三个单元
that have as their car pointer
它们的CAR指针
the object which is either 1, 2 or 3 or 4.
分别指向对象(1 2)、3以及4
And then of course the 1, 2,
当然这个(1 2)
the car of this entire structure,
即整个结构的CAR
is itself a substructure
本身就是一个子结构
which contains a sublist like that.
包含一个像这样的子表
What I'm about to do
我要做的是
is put down places which are--
就是按照下标
I'm going to assign indices.
把它们放进去
Like this 1, over here,
像这里的1
represents the index of this cell.
代表了这个格子的下标
But that pointer that we see here
这里的指针
is a reference to the
是对THE-CARS
pair of pigeonholes in the cars and the cdrs
和THE-CDRS里的小格子的引用
that are labeled by 1
它在我的线性内存中
in my linear memory down here.
被标记为1的地方
So if I wish to impose this structure
如果我想把这个结构
on my linear memory,
塞进线性内存中
what I do is I say, oh yes,
要做的是
why don't we drop this into cell 1?
把它放进格子1中
Well I said, I pick 1.
我要选取1号格子
There's 1. OK?
这个就是1号格子
And that says that its car,
这是它的CAR
I'm going to assign it to be a pair.
我要把它赋值给一个序对
It's a pair,
这个序对
which is in index 5.
序号是5
And the cdr,
它的CDR
which is this one over here,
就是这个
is a pair
它是个序对
which I'm going to stick into place 2.
我会把它放到2的位置
p2.
即P2
And take a look at p2.
我们看P2
Oh yes, well p2 is a thing
P2的CAR
whose car is the number 3,
是数字3
so as you see, an n3.
如你所见N3
And whose cdr, over here,
这里 它的CDR
is a pair,
是一个序对
which lives in place 4.
在位置4
So that's what this p4 is.
这就是P4
p4 is a number
P4是一个数字
whose value is 4 in its car
它的CAR部分是数字4
and whose cdr
它的CDR
is an empty list right there.
是个空表 就在这儿
And that ends it.
这个表就结束了
So this is the traditional way of representing
这就是在线性内存中
this kind of binary tree in a linear memory.
表示二叉树的传统方式
Now the next question, of course,
那么 下一个问题是
that we might want to worry about
我们需要关心
is just a little bit of implementation.
如何去实现
That means that when I write procedures
这意味着当我写下一个过程
of the form assigned a,
用来给A赋值时
lines of register machine code
使用寄存机器的代码来编写的
of the form assigned a, the car of fetch of b,
(ASSIGN A (FETCH B))
what I really mean
我实际上想做的是
is addressing these elements.
定位这些元素
And so we're going to think of that as
那段机器代码只是
a abbreviation for it.
这个复杂过程的简写
Now of course in order to write that down
当然 为了把它“写下来”
I'm going to introduce some sort of a structure
我要引入一种
called a vector.
称为“向量”的结构
And we're going to have something which will
我们得有一种东西
reference a vector,
用来引用向量
just so we can write it down.
这样我们就能把它写下来
Which takes the name of the vector,
它的参数之一是向量的名字
or the-- I don't think that name is the right word.
我觉得这个名字起得不太靠谱
Which takes the vector and the index,
它接受VECTOR和INDEX两个参数
and I have to have a way of setting one of those
我可以用VECTOR-SET!
with something called a vector set,
来为其中的分量赋值
I don't really care.
我不太在意
But let's look, for example,
我们来看一看
at then that kind of implementation
在这种实现中
of car and cdr.
CAR和CDR是什么样子的
So for example if I happen to have
比如说 如果我刚好有
a register b,
一个寄存器B
which contains the type index of a pair,
它存了一个序对的下标
and therefore it is the pointer to a pair,
即它是指向一个序对的指针
then I could take the car of that and
我可以取它的CAR
OK if I-- write this down-- I might put that in register a.
存到寄存器A里面
What that really is is a representation of
事实上它是
the assign to a,
把A赋值为--
the value of vector reffing--
引用向量的一个分量--
or array indexing, if you will-- or something,
或者你可以把它叫做索引一个数组
the cars object--
目标向量为THE-CARS
whatever that is-- with the index, b.
而目标分量是B
And similarly for cdr.
CDR的操作也类似
And we can do the same thing
我们可以用同样的方式
for assignment to data structures,
来对数据结构赋值
If we need to do that sort of things at all.
如果我们需要这么做的话
It's not too hard to build that.
构建这个并不太难
Well now the next question is
下一个问题是
how are we going to do allocation.
我们如何分配它们
And every so often I say I want a cons.
我们经常需要一个新的序对
Now conses don't grow on trees.
当然 CONS并没有长在树上
Or maybe they should.
或许它们应该那样
But I have to have some way
我必须得有某种方法
I have to have some way of getting the next one.
来获得一个可用的序对
I have to have some idea of
我需要某种方案
if their memory is unused
当内存不再使用的时候
that I might want to allocate from.
我可以重新分配它们
And there are many schemes for doing this.
有很多方案可以实现这一点
And the particular thing I'm showing you right now
现在我给你们展示的这个东西
is not essential.
并是不必要的
However it's convenient
然而它很方便
and has been done many times.
并且被实现很多次了
It's one schemes called the free list allocation scheme.
其中一种基于“空闲表”的分配方案
What that means is
它的意思就是
that all of the free memory that there is in the world
世界上所有的空闲内存
is linked together in a linked list,
都连在一个链表中
just like all the other stuff.
就像其它东西一样
And whenever you need a free cell
每当你需要一个新的格子
to make a new cons,
来进行CONS的时候
you grab the first one
你选择第一个格子
make the free list be the cdr of it,
将它的CDR指向空闲表
and then allocate that.
然后分配它
And so what that looks like is something like this.
就像这样
Here we have the free list
这里 我们的空闲表
starting in 6.
就是从6开始
And what that is is a pointer-off to say 8.
它是一个指向8的指针
So what it says is,
它表示
this one is free
当前这个是空闲的
and the next one is an 8.
下一个在位置8
This one is free
这个是空闲的
and the next one is in 3,
下一个在位置3
the next one that's free.
下一个是空闲的
That one's free
这个是空闲的
and the next one is in 0.
下一个在位置0
That one's free
这个是空闲的
and the next one's in 15.
下一个在位置15
Something like that.
以此类推
We can imagine having such a structure.
我们可以想象有这样的结构
Given that we have something like that,
一旦我们有了这样的机制
then it's possible to
那么当你需要空间的时候
just get one when you need it.
就能获取一个
And so a program for doing cons,
那些使用了CONS的程序
this is what cons might turn into.
内存可能就是像这样的
To assign to a register A the result of cons-ing,
把B和C进行CONS之后的值
a B onto C,
赋值给A寄存器
the value in this containing B and the value containing C,
结果包括B和C
what we have to do is
我们要做的是
get the current tail ahead of the freelist,
把当前的尾部格子 即空闲表的前个格子
make the free list be its cdr.
让它的CDR指向空闲表
Then we have to change the cars
我们要把THE-CARS中
to be the thing we're making up to be in A
由A索引的格子
to be the B, the thing in B.
修改为B中的内容
And we have to make change the cdrs of
THE-CDRS中由A索引的格子
the thing that's in A to be C.
修改为C的值
And then what we have in A
现在A所指的格子里面
is the right new frob, whatever it is.
就是新构建好的对象了
The object that we want.
这就是我们要的对象
Now there's a little bit of
我之前告诉过你们
a cheat here that I haven't told you about,
这里撒了个谎
which is somewhere around here
也就是在这里的某处
I haven't set the type of the thing that I've
我本来应该
the type of the thing
把我CONS起来的对象
that I'm cons-ing up to be a pair,
设置为序对类型
and I ought to.
但我没有
So there should be some sort of bits here are being set,
因此这里应该需要设置一些比特位
and I just haven't written that down.
我只是还没把它写下来
We could have arranged it, of course,
当然 这个很好实现
for the free list to be made out of pairs.
因为空闲表本来就是用序对实现的
And so then there's no problem with that.
因此这是没问题的
But that sort of--
但这也就是--
again, an inessential detail in a way
这些都是无关紧要的细节
some particular programmer or architect
取决于那些想要自制
or whatever might manufacture
计算机或Lisp系统的
his machine or Lisp system.
程序员或架构师
So for example,
例如
just looking at this,
看这个
to allocate
假设我们要为
given that I had already the structure that you saw before,
这个之前见过的数据结构分配空间
supposing I wanted to allocate a new cell,
假设我要分配一个新格子
which is going to be representation of list one, one, two,
来表示表(1 1 2)
where already one two was the car
其中(1 2)又是
of the list we were playing with before.
之前一个表的CAR元素
Well that's not so hard.
这不怎么难
I stored that one in one,
我用1号单元来存放数字“1”
so p1 one is the representation of this.
那么P1表示的就是这个单元
This is p5.
这个是P5
That's going to be the cdr of this.
它是应该是这个的CDR
Now we're going to pull something off the free list,
现在我们要从空闲表中取出一些东西
but remember the free list started at six.
空闲表现在是从6开始的
The new free list after this allocation is eight,
而在分配之后 空闲表将从8开始
a free list beginning at eight.
一个从8开始的空闲表
And of course
当然
in six now we have a number one,
现在6里面是数字1
which is what we wanted,
就是我们想要的
with its cdr being the pair starting in location five.
它的CDR是在位置5的序对
And that's no big deal.
没费多少力气
So the only problem really remaining here is,
这里依然存在的一个问题是
well, I don't have an infinitely large memory.
我们没有无限大的内存
If I do this for a little while,
如果我像这么操作了一会儿
say, for example,
比如说
supposing it takes me a microsecond to do a cons,
假设进行一次CONS花费1微秒
and I have a million cons memory
如果要进行一百万次CONS
then I'm only going to run out in a second,
那么我就要消耗1秒钟的时间
and that's pretty bad.
这就很糟糕了
So what we do to prevent that disaster,
如何预防这样的灾难
that ecological disaster,
这种生态灾难
talk about right after questions.
在提问环节之后我们再继续讨论
Are there any questions?
有人要提问吗?
Yes.
请讲
AUDIENCE: In the environment diagrams that we were drawing
学生：在环境图表中
we would use the body of procedures,
我们画了过程体
and you would eventually wind up with
但是在过程应用结束后
things that were no longer useful in that structure.
这些环境中的东西就不再有用了
PROFESSOR: Yes, madam.
教授：说得很对
AUDIENCE: How is that represented?
学生：它是如何表示的？
PROFESSOR: There's two problems here. OK?
教授：这其实是两个问题
One you were asking
第一个问题是
is that material becomes useless.
材料没用了
We'll talk about that in a second.
我们稍后就会讲
That has to do with how to prevent ecological disasters.
如何预防生态灾难
Right? If I make a lot of garbage
如果我制造了一堆垃圾
I have to somehow be able to clean up after myself.
我需要自己清理掉
And we'll talk about that in a second.
我们一会儿就要讲
The other question you're asking
第二个问题
is how you represent the environments, I think.
你问的是如何表示环境
AUDIENCE: Yes.
学生：对
PROFESSOR: OK.
教授：好
And the environment structures can be represented in arbitrary ways.
环境结构能够以任意的方式表示
There are lots of them.
有很多种表示方式
I mean, here I'm just telling you about list cells.
这里 我只讲了基于表结构的内存
Of course every real system
当然 每个真实的系统
has vectors of arbitrary length
都有任意长度的向量
as well as the vectors of length, too,
也有固定长度的向量
which represent list cells.
它们都可以作为内存的表示方法
And the environment structures that one uses in a
在一个专业的Lisp系统中
professionally written Lisp system
环境结构是用
tend to be vectors
向量表示的
which contain a number of elements approximately
它所包含的元素的数量
equal to the number of arguments-- a little bit more
比参数的个数稍微多一点
because you need sort of glue.
因为你需要某种“粘合剂”
OK? So remember, the environment is in a frame.
记住环境是在框架里的
The frames are constructed by applying a procedure.
框架是应用过程时被构建出来的
In doing so,
这种情况下
an allocation is made of a place
所分配的空间大小为
which is the number of arguments long plus some glue
实际参数加上“粘合剂”占用的空间
that gets linked into a chain.
然后将它连接到某条链上
It's just like algol at that level.
在这个层次上 和ALGOL差不多
There any other questions?
还有其它问题吗?
OK.
好
Thank you, and let's take a short break.
谢谢 我们休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
存储分配与垃圾收集
PROFESSOR: Well, as I just said,
教授：如同我刚才说过的那样
computer memories
半导体厂商
supplied by the semiconductor manufacturers
所生产的计算机内存
are finite.
容量是有限的
And that's quite a pity.
这的确很可惜
It might not always be that way.
但它也可能不总是这样
Just for a quick calculation,
简单算一下
you can see that it's possible that if memory's
你可以看到 如果内存的价格
prices keep going at the rate they're going
继续保持当前的趋势的话
that if you still took a microsecond second to do a cons,
如果你执行CONS的时候也只需要1微秒
then-- first of all, everybody
那么 首先大家知道
should know that there's about pi
一年大约有
times ten to the seventh seconds in a year.
PI*10^7秒
And so that would be
那么就有
ten to the seventh plus ten to the sixth
10^6乘以10^7
is ten to the thirteenth.
也就是10^13
So there's maybe ten to the fourteenth conses
那么在机器的一生中
in the life of a machine.
就能有10^14个CONS
If there was ten to the fourteenth words of memory
如果你的机器上
on your machine,
有10^14个字的内存
you'd never run out.
你就永远不会用完
OK so that will be,
这样就会……
And that's not completely unreasonable.
这并不是完全没有道理
Ten to the fourteenth is not a very large number.
10^14次方不是个非常大的数字
Even for... I don't think it is.
我不觉得它是个很大的数字
But then again I like to play with astronomy.
但我喜欢在天文学领域进行比较
It's at least ten to the eighteenth centimeters
距离我们最近的星星
between us and the nearest star.
至少有10^18次方厘米远
But the thing I'm about to worry about is,
我担心的是
at least in the current economic state of affairs,
至少以现在的经济状况
ten to the fourteenth pieces of memory is expensive.
10^14大小的内存很贵
And so I suppose what we have to do
因此我认为我们需要
is make do with much smaller memories.
适应更小的内存
Now
现在
in general we want to have an illusion of infinity.
广义地说 我们营造一种无限内存的假象
All we need to do is arrange it
我们需要整理它
so that whenever you look, the thing is there.
以便在我们需要内存的时候就能获得它
That's, that's really an important idea.
这个想法非常重要
A person or a computer lives only a finite amount of time
人或者计算机只能存在有限的时间
and can only take a finite number of looks at something.
只能看有限的东西
And so you really only need a finite amount of stuff.
因此你只需要有限的东西
But you have to arrange it
只要你合理地安排它们
so no matter how much there is,
使得不管实际有多少内存
how much you really claim there is,
你要求这里有多少
there's always enough stuff
当你去看的时候
so that when you take a look, it's there.
总有足够的东西
And so you only need a finite amount.
因此你只需要有限的数量
But let's see.
我们来看看
One problem is, as was brought up,
我们之前提过一个问题
that there are possible ways
在很多情况下
that there is lots of stuff
我们制造了大量
that we make that we don't need.
不需要的东西
And we could recycle the material out of which its made.
我们可以进行回收再利用
An example
举个例子
for is, is the fact
事实上
when we're building environment structures,
当我们调用一个过程的时候
and we do so every time we call a procedure.
都会构建环境结构
We have built in it a environment frame.
我们把它构建在一个环境框架中
That environment frame
这个环境框架
doesn't necessarily have a very long lifetime.
不用存在很长时间
Its lifetime, meaning its usefulness,
只有在进行过程调用的时候
may exist only over the invocation of the procedure.
它的存在才是有用的
Or if the procedure exports another procedure
如果过程把另一个过程
by returning it as a value
作为返回值返回
and that procedure is defined inside of it,
并且这个过程是在它的内部定义的
well then the lifetime of the
那么外层过程的
frame of the outer procedure still is
存活时间仍然是
only the lifetime of the procedure
被返回的过程的
which was exported.
存活时间
And so ultimately,
最终
a lot of that is garbage.
就会制造很多垃圾
There are other ways of producing garbage as well.
还有其它的途径可以制造垃圾
Users produce garbage.
用户也会制造垃圾
An example of
举例来说
user garbage is something like this.
用户制造的垃圾像是这样
If we write a program to, for example,
如果我们写个程序
append two lists together,
把两个表连接到一起
well one way to do it is to
唯一的办法是
reverse the first list onto the empty list
把第一个表逆序塞到空表中
and reverse that onto the second list.
再把新表逆序塞到第二个表中
Now that's not terribly bad way of doing it.
这种解法并不是很糟糕
And however,
然而
the intermediate result,
程序所生成的
which is the reversal of the first list
中间结果
as done by this program,
即第一个表的逆序表
is never going to be accessed ever again
在它被复制到第二个表之后
after it's copied back on to the second.
就再也不会被用到了
It's an intermediate result.
它是个中间结果
It's going to be hard to ever see
它很难被找到
how anybody would ever be able to access it.
没有人能访问到它
In fact, it will go away.
事实上 它会消失掉
Now if we make a lot of garbage like that,
如果我们像这样制造了大量的垃圾
and we should be allowed to,
系统也应该允许我们这么干
then there's got to be some way to reclaim that garbage.
但应该有某些方法去回收这些垃圾
Well, what I'd like to tell you about now
现在 我要告诉你
is a very clever technique
一个非常聪明的技巧
whereby a Lisp system
一个Lisp系统
can prove a small theorem every so often
通常可以证明一条小定理
on the form the following piece of junk
也就是 某段内存中的值
will never be accessed again.
之后不再会被用到
It can have no affect on the future of the computation.
它对以后的计算没有任何影响
It's actually based on a very simple idea.
事实上 这基于一个很简单的想法
We've designed our computers to look sort of like this.
我们已经把计算机设计成这个样子
There's some data path,
有一些数据通路
which contains the registers.
其中有寄存器
You know, there are things like exp, and env,
有EXP、ENV
and val, and so on.
和VAL之类的寄存器
And there's one here called stack,
这里有个叫STACK的东西
some sort which points off to a structure somewhere,
某种指向一个结构的东西
which is the stack.
它是个栈
And we'll worry about that in a second.
我们过一会再研究它
There's some finite controller,
这里有一些
finite state machine controller.
有穷状态控制器
And there's some control signals that go this way and
控制信号在这之间流通
predicate results that come this way,
比如谓词的返回结果
not the interesting part.
这部分并不太有趣
There's some sort of structured memory,
这里有某种结构化的内存
which I just told you how to make,
我刚才给你讲过如何构建它
which may contain a stack.
它可能包括一个栈
I didn't tell you how to make things
我没有告诉你如何把东西
of arbitrary shape,
构建成任意形状
only pairs.
只有序对
But in fact
但事实上
with what I've told you can
我告诉过你
with what I've told you can simulate a stack by a big list.
可以用一张大表来模拟栈
I don't plan to do that,
我没准备干这个
it's not a nice way to do it.
这不是个好办法
But we could have something like that.
但是我们可以有这样一个东西
We have all sorts of little data structures in here
这里有各种数据结构
that are hooked together in funny ways.
它们通过有趣的方式互相连接
They connect to other things.
它们和其它东西连接到一起
And so on.
以此类推
And ultimately
归根结底
things up there are pointers to these.
这里的东西是指向这里的指针
The things that are in the registers
寄存器里的指针
are pointers off to the data structures
指向的是表结构内存中
that live in this list structure memory.
数据结构
Now the truth of the matter is
现在 我们的问题是
that the entire consciousness
机器的整个意识
of this machine is in these registers.
是在寄存器里的
There is no possible way that the machine,
如果这个机器
if done correctly, if built correctly,
构建得正确的话
can access anything in this list structure memory
它无法访问表结构内存中任何的东西
unless the thing in that list structure memory is
除非这个表结构内存中的数据
is connected by a sequence of data structures
通过一系列的数据结构
to the registers.
与寄存器相连接
If it's accessible
如果它能够
by legitimate data structure selectors
被合法的数据结构选择函数访问到
from the pointers that are stored in these registers.
通过寄存器里保存的指针能够访问它
Things like array references, perhaps.
比如说 数组引用
Or cons cell references, cars and cdrs.
或者针对序对的引用--CAR或者CDR
But I can't just talk about a random place in this memory,
但我不能随意访问内存中的位置
because I can't get to it.
因为我找不到它
These are being arbitrary names I'm not allowed to count,
至少在我求值某条表达式的时候
at least as I'm evaluating expressions.
我是不允许去访问那个任意名字的
If that's the case
如果是这样的话
then there's a very simple theorem to be proved.
就可以证明一个简单的理论
Which is,
就是说
if I start with all lead pointers that are in all these registers
如果我从这些寄存器指向的地方开始
and recursively chase out,
递归地遍历
marking all the places I can get to by selectors,
标记选择函数所有能访问到内存
then eventually I mark everything they can be gotten to.
最终就能标记所有能访问的东西
Anything which is not so marked is garbage
任何未标记的都是垃圾
and can be recycled.
它们可以被回收
Very simple.
非常简单
Cannot affect the future of the computation.
不会影响之后的计算
So let me show you that in a particular
我来举一个
in a particular example.
具体的例子
Now that means I'm going to have to append to my
在此之前 需要给我的表结构内存
description of the list structure a mark.
添加一个叫MARK的标志位
And so here, for example,
因此 在这里
is a list structured memory.
就有一个表结构内存
And in this list structured memory
这块表内存中
is a list structure
存放了一个表数据结构
beginning in a place I'm going to call--
我们把这个起始位置
this is the root.
称为“根”
Now it doesn't really have to have a root.
不一定只有一个根
It could be a bunch of them, like all the registers.
与寄存器类似 可以有很多这种东西
But I could cleverly arrange it
但我可以巧妙地安排它们
so all the registers, all the things that are in old registers
把所有在旧寄存器里的东西
are also at the right moment
在何时的时间点
put into this root structure,
放入到这个根结构中
and then we've got one pointer to it.
然后用一个指针指向它
I don't really care.
这不是重点
So the idea is
思路就是
we're going to cons up stuff
我们要不断地进行CONS
until our free list is empty.
直到空闲表为空
We've run out of things.
这样就用尽了所有空间
Now we're going to do this process of proving the theorem
现在我们要证明这个理论
that a certain percentage of the memory
也就是一部分的内存
is got crap in it.
已经没有用了
And then we're going to recycle that
然后我们要回收它
to grow new trees,
构建一个新的树
a standard use of such garbage.
这是这些垃圾的标准使用方式
So in any case, what do we have here?
那么我们要做什么呢?
Well we have some data structure
从P5这个位置开始
which starts out over here in p5.
存了一些数据结构
Sorry, and it will start at one
说错了--是从1开始
And in fact
事实上
it has a car in p5,
它的CAR部分存放在P5这个位置
and its cdr is in two.
而CDR部分存在在P2这个位置
And all the marks start out at zero.
最开始 所有的标记都是0
Well let's start marking, just to play this game.
我们要开始标记了
OK.
好
So for example,
例如
since I can access one from the root
因为我可以从根访问到位置P1
I will mark that.
我就标记一下
Let me mark it.
我来标一下
Bang.
好了
That's marked.
这个被标记了
OK. Now since I have a five here
因为它指向位置P5
I can go to five
所以我来到了5号格子
and see, well I'll mark that.
然后 我要标记这个
Bang.
标好了
That's useful stuff.
这个笔真好用
But five references as a number in its car,
但是5号位置的CAR部分是一个数字
I'm not interested in marking numbers
我对标记数字不感兴趣
but its cdr is seven.
但它的CDR部分是P7
So I can mark that.
所以我可以标记它
Bang.
又标好了
OK? Seven is the empty list,
P7的CDR部分是空表
the only thing that references,
而它唯一所引用的元素则是
and it's got a number in its car.
它的CAR部分是个数字
Not interesting.
我对它不感兴趣
Well now let's go back here.
让我们回到这里
I forgot about something.
我忘记了一些事情
Two.
P2
See in other words, if I'm looking at cell one,
换句话说 如果我看1号格子
cell one contains a two right over here.
1号格子的CDR部分指向P2
A reference to two.
一个指向P2的引用
That means I should go mark two.
这意味着我应该标记P2
Bang.
好了
Two contains a reference to four.
P2包含了了一个到P4的引用
It's got a number in its car,
而P2的CAR部分是个数字
I'm not interested in that
我对它不感兴趣
so I'm going to go mark that.
所以我要标记P4
Four refers to seven through its car,
P4的CAR部分引用了P7
and is empty in its cdr,
它的CDR是空的
but I've already marked that one
但由于我已经标记过P7了
so I don't have to mark it again.
就不再次标记它了
This is all the accessible structure
这就是这个地方
from that place.
所能访问的所有单元
Simple recursive mark algorithm.
很简单的递归标记算法
Now there are some unhappinesses about that algorithm,
这个算法有一些不足的地方
and we can worry about that a second.
我们稍后会说
But basically you'll see
但基本上你能看到
that all the things that have not been marked
所有没被标记的地方
are places that are free,
都是无用的
and I could recycle.
可以回收
So the next stage after that is going to be
所以下一步就是
to scan through all of my memory,
扫描整个内存
looking for things that are not marked.
寻找未被标记的格子
Every time I come across a marked thing
每当遇到一个已标记的格子
I unmark it,
就把标记去掉
and every time I come across an unmarked thing
每当遇到未标记的格子时
I'm going to link it together in my free list.
我就把它连接到我的空闲表中
Classic, very simple algorithm.
传统而且非常简单的算法
So let's see.
我们来看看
Is that very simple?
它很简单吗?
Yes it is.
是的
I'm not going to go through the code in any detail,
我不会深入代码细节
but I just want to show you about how long it is.
只是想给你看看它有多长
Let's look at the mark phase.
看这个标记阶段
Here's the first part of the mark phase.
这是标记阶段的第一部分
We pick up the root.
我们找到根
We're going to do some
我们要
We're going to use that as a recursive procedure call.
对它进行递归过程调用
We're going to sweep from there,
当我们完成标记之后
after when we're done with marking.
就从这里开始清除
And then we're going to do a little couple of instructions
然后我们将执行一些指令
that do this checking out on the marks
来检查这些标记
and changing the marks and things like that,
或者更改这些标记
according to the algorithm I've just shown you.
按照我刚才讲的那个算法进行
OK? It comes out here.
代码在这里
You have to mark the cars of things
你需要标记它们的CAR
and you also have to be able to mark the cdrs of things.
也需要标记它们的CDR
That's the entire mark phase.
这就是整个标记阶段
I'll just tell you a little story about this.
我给你讲个关于它的小故事
The old DEC PDP-6 computer,
古董货DEC PDP-6计算机
this was the way that
它上面的
the mark-sweep garbage collection, as it was, was written.
标记-清除垃圾回收系统就是这么写的
The program was so small
程序很短
that with the data that it needed,
以至于它需要的数据
with the registers that it needed to manipulate the memory,
以及用来操作内存的所需的寄存器
it fit into the fast registers of the machine,
都能够放入到计算机的
which were 16.
16个快速寄存器中
The whole program.
整个程序
And you could execute instructions in the fast registers.
你可以在快速寄存器里执行指令
So it's an extremely small program,
所以这是个非常小的程序
and it could run very fast.
它跑得飞快
Now unfortunately, of course,
然而很不幸
this program, because the fact that it's recursive
因为这个程序是递归的
in the way that you do something first
因为你需要先做某件事儿
and then you do something after that,
然后再去做另外一件事儿
you have to work on the cars and then the cdrs,
你得先处理CAR 再处理CDR
it requires auxiliary memory.
这就需要辅助内存
So Lisp systems--
所以Lisp系统
those requires a stack for marking.
需要一个栈来进行标记
Lisp systems that are built this way
Lisp系统通过这样的方式
have a limit to the depth of recursion you can have
限制了你在数据结构上
in data structures in either the car or the cdr,
进行CAR或者CDR递归的深度
and that doesn't work very nicely.
这并不太靠谱
On the other hand,
另外一方面
you never notice it if it's big enough.
当它足够大的时候你不会发现
And that's certainly been
例如 这样的情况
the case for most Maclisp, for example,
发生在大多数MacLisp系统上
which ran Macsyma
在它上面运行的Macsyma
where you could deal with expressions
允许你处理
of thousands of elements long.
有成千上万个元素的表达式
These are algebraic expressions with thousand of terms.
有很多代数式有大量的项
And there's no problem with that.
这没什么问题
Such, the garbage collector does work.
垃圾回收器能正常工作
On the other hand,
另一方面
there's a very clever modification to this algorithm,
这个算法有个很精妙的修改版
which I will not describe,
但我不会去讲
by Peter Deutsch and Schorr and Waite--
它是由Peter Deutsch
and Schorr and Waite, Herb Schorr from IBM
来自IBM的Herb Schorr
and Waite who I don't know.
和我不太认识的Waite所提出
Whrere... That algorithm
这个算法
allows you build
可以不使用
you do can do this without auxiliary memory,
额外的辅助内存
by remembering as you walk the data structures
只需要在遍历整个数据结构的时候
where you came from by reversing the pointers as you go down
记住你是从哪里来的并反转指针
and crawling up the reverse pointers as you go up.
回溯的时候 再去反转这个指针
It's a rather tricky algorithm.
这是个很取巧的算法
The first time you write it--
你第一次写它的时候
or in fact, the first three times you write it it
事实上 你前三次写它的时候
it has a terrible bug in it.
都会遇到严重的BUG
And it's also about, it's quite rather slow,
也可能奇慢无比
because it's complicated.
因为这个算法太复杂了
It takes about six times as many memory references
它用了大概六倍的内存引用
to do the sorts of things that we're talking about.
来完成我们刚才讨论的任务
Well now once I've done this marking phase,
一旦我完成了标记阶段
and I get into a position where things look like this,
我们就面临着这样的状况
let's look-- yes.
请看
Here we have the mark done,
这里完成了标记工作
just as I did it.
和我刚才描述的一样
Now we have to perform the sweep phase.
现在我们要进行清除阶段
And I described to you what this sweep is like.
我刚才已经讲过如何清除了
I'm going to walk down from one end of memory or the other,
我要从内存的一端开始
I don't care where,
哪一端都可以
scanning every cell that's in the memory.
扫描内存中的每个格子
And as I scan these cells,
在扫描的同时
I'm going to link them together,
如果是空闲内存
if they are free, into the free list.
就把它们连接到空闲表中
And if they're not free,
如果它们不是空闲内存
I'm going to unmark them so the marks become zero.
我就把它们的标记清除掉
And in fact what I get--
事实上
well the program is not very complicated.
最终的程序并不很复杂
It looks sort of like this-- it's a little longer.
它只是变长了一些
Here's the first piece of it.
这是第一部分
This one's coming down from the top of memory.
它从内存的顶端向下遍历
I don't want you to try to understand this at this point.
我不期望你现在就搞懂它
It's rather simple.
它挺简单的
It's a very simple algorithm,
这是个非常简单的算法
but there's pieces of it that just sort of look like this.
其中的一段代码像是这样
They're all sort of obvious.
非常显而易见
And after we've done the sweep,
在清理结束后
we get an answer that looks like that.
我们就得到了像这样的结果
Now there are some disadvantages
这种标记-清除算法
with mark-sweep algorithms of this sort.
有一些缺点
Serious ones.
最严重的一个是
One important disadvantage is
最严重的缺点是
that your memories get larger and larger.
当你的内存越来越大
As you say, address spaces get larger and larger,
地址空间也就会越来越大
you're willing to represent more and more stuff,
你想用它存更多东西
then it gets very costly to scan all of memory.
那么扫描整个内存就会非常耗时
What you'd really like to do
你真正想做的是
is only scan useful stuff.
只扫描有用的东西
It would even be better
这样就会好一点
if you realized that some stuff
如果你意识到
was known to be good and useful,
哪些东西已知是有用的
and you don't have to look at it more than once or twice.
你就没必要去多次检查它
Or very rarely.
或者不用经常去检查它
Whereas other stuff that you're not so sure about,
对于那些你不太确定的
you can look at more detail
你可以在每次需要的时候
every time you want to do this,
进行仔细检查
want to garbage collect.
也就是垃圾收集的时候
Well there are algorithms
这些算法
that are organized in this way.
就是用了这样的方法
Let me tell you about a famous old algorithm
我要介绍一个著名的古老算法
which allows you only look at
这种算法允许你
the part of memory which is known to be useful.
只检查内存中已知是有用的部分
And which happens to be
这让它成为了
the fastest known garbage collector algorithm.
目前已知最快的垃圾收集算法
This is the Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson garbage collector algorithm.
它就是 Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson 垃圾收集算法
It was invented by Minsky
它是由Minsky
in 1961 or '60 or something,
在1960、61年左右发明的
for the RLE PDP-1 Lisp,
当时是给RLE PDP-1 Lisp用的
which had 4,096 words of list memory,
这个机器只有4096个字的线性内存
and a drum.
还有个磁鼓
And the whole idea
为了能够
was to garbage collect this terrible memory.
在这种恶劣的条件下进行垃圾收集
What Minsky realized
Minsky意识到
was the easiest way to do this
达成目的最容易的方法是
is to scan the memory in the same sense,
在扫描内存的同时
walking the good structure,
遍历那些好的数据结构
copying it out into the drum,
把它复制到磁鼓中
compacted.
压缩一下
And then when we were done copying it all out,
之后把它们复制出来
then you swap that back into your memory.
并把它们交换回内存里
Now whether or you not use a drum,
不管是使用的是磁鼓
or another piece of memory,
或者其它的内存
or something like that isn't important.
这都不重要
In fact,
事实上
I don't think people use drums anymore for anything.
我觉得现在应该没人用磁鼓了吧
But this algorithm basically
但这个算法基本上
depends upon having
要依赖于
about twice as much address space
大约两倍于
you're actually using.
你实际使用的内存
And so what you have is some, initially,
最开始的情况是
some mixture of useful data and garbage.
有用的数据和垃圾混在了一起
So this is called fromspace.
它被称为FROMSPACE
And this is a mixture of crud.
这是CRUD的混合
Some of it's important and some of it isn't.
有些是有用的 有些没有用
Now there's another place
现在还有另外一块空间
which is hopefully big enough,
它需要足够大
if we recall, tospace,
这个地方叫TOSPACE
which is where we're copying to.
要把东西复制进去
And what happens is--
接下来会发生的是
and I'm not going to go through this detail.
我不会深入细节
It's in our book quite explicitly.
书上写得很清楚了
There's a root point where you start from.
这里有一个根节点
And the idea is that you start with the root.
你从根节点开始
You copy the first thing you see,
复制你看到的第一个东西
the first thing that the root points at,
根指针指向的第一个东西
to the beginning of tospace.
复制到TOSPACE的头部
The first thing is a pair
这些东西一般是一个序对
or something like, a data structure.
或者是类似的数据结构
You then also leave behind
然后在那里留下
a broken heart saying,
一颗“破碎的心”
I moved this object from here to here,
表示我把东西从这里移动到了这里
giving the place where it moved to.
指示了移动的目的地
This is called a broken heart because
叫作破碎的心是因为
a friend of mine who implemented
我的一个朋友
one of these in 1966
在1966年实现了这个算法
was a very romantic character
而他是个文艺青年
and called it a broken heart.
就取名叫“破碎的心”
But in any case,
不论如何
the next thing you do
接下来要做的是
is now you have a new free pointer which is here,
FREE指针现在指向这里
and you start scanning.
然后开始扫描
You scan this data structure you just copied.
扫描这个刚复制过来的数据结构
And every time you encounter a pointer in it,
每当你遇到其中的指针
you treat it as if it was the root pointer here.
你把它当作是这里的根指针
Oh, I'm sorry.
哦 不好意思
The other thing you do
我们还需要做的是
is you now move the root pointer to there.
你将根指针移动到这里
So now you scan this,
因此在扫描的过程中
and everything you see
把遇到的每个指针
you treat as it were the root pointer.
都可以当作是ROOT指针
So if you see something,
如果你遇到了某个指针
well it points up into there somewhere.
指向了这里的某个地方
Is it pointing at a thing
它指向的东西
which you've not copied yet?
你复制过了吗？
Is there a broken heart there?
这里是“破碎的心”吗
If there's a broken heart there
如果那里是破碎的心
and it's something you have copied,
就说明那里的东西复制过了
you've just replaced this pointer
只需要用破碎的心所指向的地址
with the thing a broken heart points at.
来替换它指针即可
If this thing has not been copied,
如果它还没被复制
you copy it to the next place over here.
你把它复制到这里
Move your free pointer over here,
把FREE指针移到这里
and then leave a broken heart behind
然后在那里放置一颗破碎的心
and scan.
继续扫描
And eventually when the scant pointer hits the free pointer,
最终SCAN指针追上了FREE指针
everything in memory has been copied.
内存里的所有东西都被复制了
And then there's a whole bunch
这样这里就剩下了
of empty space up here,
大量的空闲空间
which you could either make into a free list,
如果你需要的话
if that's what you want to do.
你可以把它组织为空闲表
But generally you don't in this kind of system.
但这种系统通常不这么来做
In this system you sequentially allocate your memory.
这类系统中 内存是顺序分配的
That is a very, very nice algorithm,
这是个非常 非常好的算法
and sort of the one we use in the
你们现在使用的Scheme系统中
the scheme that you've been using.
就使用了这种算法
And it's known to be... it's expected--
它应该是--
I believe no one has found
我相信还没有人发现
a faster algorithm than that.
比它跑得更快的算法
There are very simple modifications to this algorithm
有一些对这个算法的简单修改
invented by Henry Baker
由Henry Baker发明
which allow one to run this algorithm in real time,
它让你能实时运行这个算法
meaning you don't have to stop to garbage collect.
也就是说进行回收时不需要暂停程序
But you could interleave the consing
你能够让机器运行时
that the machine does when its running
进行的各种CONS操作
with steps of the garbage collection process,
与垃圾回收过程交错进行
so that the thing, the garbage collector's distributed
垃圾回收器是分散的
and the machine doesn't have to stop,
机器不需要停下来
and garbage collecting can start.
再让垃圾回收开始运作
Of course in the case of machines with virtual memory
当然 在使用虚拟内存的机器中
where a lot of it is in inaccessible places,
有很多内存无法访问
this becomes a very expensive process.
这会让整个过程变得耗时
And there have been numerous
有很多人尝试
attempts to make this much better.
将它改进得更好
There is a nice paper,
对于感兴趣的同学
for those of you who are interested,
这有一篇论文
by Moon and other people
作者是Moon等人
which describes a modification to
这篇论文描述了
the incremental Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson algorithm,
增量式Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson算法
and modification the Baker algorithm
和Baker算法的修改
which is more efficient for virtual memory systems.
让使用虚拟内存的系统更加高效
Well I think now the mystery to this is sort of gone.
现在最后一个谜团也解开了
And I'd like to see if there are any questions.
有什么疑惑吗？
Yes.
请讲
AUDIENCE: I saw one of you run the garbage collector
学生：我在楼上的系统上
on the systems upstairs,
你们运行垃圾收集器的时候
and it seemed to me to run extremely fast.
它看起来跑得飞快
PROFESSOR: Yes
教授：是的
AUDIENCE: Did the whole thing take--
学生：整个过程花费了--
does it sweep through all of memory?
它真的扫描了整个内存吗？
PROFESSOR: No.
教授：没有
It swept through exactly what was needed
它只扫描了那些需要的
to copy the useful structure.
去复制那些有用的数据结构
It's a copying collector.
它是个复制收集器
AUDIENCE: OK.
学生：好吧
PROFESSOR: And it's rather... it is very fast.
教授：但它确实很快
On the whole, I suppose to copy in a Bobcat
整体来说 我想如果要复制
to copy, I think, a three megabyte thing or something
一个大约3MB的东西
is less than a second,
将在一秒内完成
real time
而且是实时的
Really, these are very small programs.
它们是非常小的程序
One thing you should realise is that
你需要注意到的一件事是
garbage collectors have to be small.
垃圾收集器必须要小
Not because they have to be fast,
不是因为它们需要运行得快
but because no one can debug
因为没有人能够调试
a complicated garbage collector.
复杂的垃圾收集器
A garbage collector, if it doesn't work,
如果一个垃圾收集器不能正常工作
will trash your memory in such a way
它会把你的内存搞得一团糟
that you cannot figure out what the hell happened.
而你却束手无策
You need an audit trail.
你需要跟踪审计
Because it rearranges everything,
因为它把所有东西都换了位置
and how do you know what happened there?
你需要知道那里发生了什么
So this is the only kind of program that
所以这是唯一一种
it really, seriously matters
真正非常重要的程序
if you stare at it long enough
如果你盯着它看足够久
so you believe that it works.
那么你就相信它有效
That means and sort of prove it to yourself.
这意味着某种“自我证明”
And that, that... So there's no way to debug it.
因此我们无法对它进行查错
And that takes it being small enough
这意味着它需要足够小
so you can hold it in your head.
你的大脑能够思考它的工作情况
So garbage collectors are special in this way.
正因如此 垃圾收集器十分特殊
So every reasonable garbage collector has gotten small,
所以实用的垃圾收集器一定要短小
and generally small programs are fast.
而通常短小的程序运行得就快
Yes.
请讲
AUDIENCE: Can you repeat the name of this technique once again?
学生：您能再重复一遍这个技术的名字吗?
PROFESSOR: That's the Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson garbage collector.
教授：Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson垃圾回收器
AUDIENCE: You got that?
学生：什么?
PROFESSOR: Minsky invented it in '61
教授：Minsky在1961年
for the RLE PDP-1.
为RLE PDP-1设计了这个算法
A version of it was developed and elaborated
Fenichel和Yochelson改进并精化了算法
to be used in Multics Maclisp by Fenichel and Yochelson
将它用在了Multics平台的MacLisp中
in somewhere around 1968 or '69.
那时大约是1968或者1969年
OK. Let's take a break.
好吧 我们休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
计算的极限
PROFESSOR: Well we've come to the end of this subject,
教授：我们已经到课程的最后一部分了
and we've already shown you a universal machine
我已经给你们展示了一台通用机器
which is down to evaluator.
它被简化为求值器
It's down to the level of detail
它被简化到
you could imagine you could make one.
你自己也能构造出来
This is a particular implementation of Lisp,
这是一个特定的Lisp实现
built on one of those
它是用
scheme chips that was talked about yesterday,
昨天讲过的Scheme芯片制作的
sitting over here.
就是这个
This is mostly interface to somebody's memory
这基本上就是暴露给他人内存的接口了
with a little bit of timing and other such stuff.
里面有节拍发生器等组件
But this fellow actually ran Lisp
尽管是解释执行
at a fairly reasonable rate, as interpretive.
但它们运行Lisp的速度还算不错
It ran Lisp as fast as a DEC PDP-10
它跑得像1979年的
back in 1979.
DEC PDP-10一样快
And so it's gotten pretty hardware.
作为一个十足的硬件
Pretty concrete.
算是十分“实在”了
We've also downed you a bit
我们为你们讲解了一些
with the things you can compute.
可以被计算的东西
But is it the case that
但我们是否可能遇到
there are things we can't compute?
我们无法计算的情况？
And so I'd like to end this with
课程的最后
showing you some things that you'd like be able to compute
我想展示一些你认为可以被计算
that you can't.
但实际上不能的东西
The answer is yes,
实际上
there are things you can't compute.
确实有我们无法计算的东西
For example,
例如
something you'd really like is--
我们想要这样的一种东西
if you're writing a compiler
当我们在编写编译器时
you'd like a program that would check
你想用一个程序检查
that the thing you're going to do will work.
你的代码能否正常运行
Wouldn't that be nice?
这不是很棒吗?
You'd like something that would catch infinite loops,
你希望能够捕获死循环
for example,
例如
in programs that were written by users.
用户编写的程序里的死循环
But in general you can't write such a program
但通常来说 你写不出这样的程序
that will read any program
它读取某个程序
and determine whether or not
并检测它
it's an infinite loop.
是不是死循环
Let me show you that.
我来展示一下
It's a little bit of a minor mathematics.
这个需要涉及到数学知识
Let's imagine
设想
that we just had a mathematical function
在我们开始之前
before we start.
有一个数学函数
And there is one,
这里就有一个
called s,
记作S
which takes a procedure
它接受一个过程
and its argument, a.
和它的参数A
And what s does
S所做的是
is it determines whether or not
检测以A为参数运行P时
it's safe to run p on a.
是否安全
And what I mean by that is this:
换句话说就是
it's true if p applied to a
如果(P A)
will converge
在没有出错的情况下
to a value
能够返回一个值
without an error.
那么S就为TRUE
And it's false
但如果(P A)
if p of a
是死循环
loops forever
或者抛出错误
or makes an error.
那么S就为FALSE
Now that's surely a function.
这确实是个函数
There is some for every procedure
对于你输入的任何过程
and for every argument you could give it
或者任何参数
that is either true or false
它只能返回TRUE或FALSE
that it converges without making an error.
它会返回一个值而且不会报错
And you could make a giant table of them.
你可以为它们画一张巨大的表格
But the question is,
但问题是
can you write a procedure
你能写一个过程
that compute the values of this function?
来计算这个函数的值吗?
Well let's assume that we can.
假设我们能做到
Suppose
假设
that we have a procedure
我们有个过程
procedure called "safe"
一个叫作SAFE?的过程
that computes the value of s.
它能计算S的值
Now I'm going to show you by several methods
现在我要用几种方法
that you can't do this.
证明你做不到
The easiest one,
最简单的一个
or the first one,
或者说第一个
let's define a procedure called diag1.
我们定义一个叫DIAG1的过程
Given that we have safe,
给定了SAFE?过程
we can define diag1
我们可以把DIAG1定义为
diag1
把DIAG1定义为
to be the procedure of one argument, p,
只含有参数P的过程
which has the following properties.
它有着这样的属性
If it's safe to apply p to itself,
如果(SAFE? P P)为真
then I wish to have an infinite loop.
那么我就主动陷入死循环
Otherwise I'm going to return 3.
否则我会返回3
Maybe it was 42.
它也可能是42
What's the answer to the big question?
宇宙的终极答案是什么?
Where of course we know what an infinite loop is.
我们当然知道死循环是什么
Infinite loop,
死循环INF是
to be a procedure of no arguments,
一个无参过程
which is that nice lambda calculus loop.
这是一个极好的LAMBADA演算循环
Lambda of x,
(LAMBDA (X) (X X))
applied to lambda of x, x of x.
应用到(LAMBDA (X) (X X))
So there's nothing left to the imagination here.
没什么想象的余地了
Well let's see what the story is.
我们来看下会发生什么
I'm supposing it's the case
我假设
that we worry about the procedure
我们考虑
called diag1 applied to diag1.
把DIAG1应用到DIAG1上
Well what could it possibly be?
那会发生什么呢?
Well I don't know.
我不知道
We're going to substitute diag1
将DIAG1代换为
for p in the body here.
P的过程体
Well is it safe to compute diag1 of diag1?
(SAFE? DIAG1 DIAG1)会返回什么呢？
I don't know.
我不知道
There are two possibilities.
有两种可能
If it's safe to compute diag1 of diag1
如果计算(DIAG1 DIAG1)是安全的
that means it shouldn't loop.
这意味着没有死循环
That means I go to here,
那么我就要来到这里
but then I produce an infinite loop.
但是随即我就陷入了死循环
So it can't be safe.
所以它不是安全的
But if it's not safe to compute diag1 of diag1
但如果计算(DIAG1 DIAG1)不安全
then the answer to this is 3.
那么它的结果是3
But that's diag1 of diag1,
但是调用(DIAG1 DIAG1)又必须能够返回
so it had to be safe.
所以它必须安全才行
So therefore by contradiction
因此 通过归纳出这个矛盾
you cannot produce safe.
我们无法写出这个SAFE?过程
For those of you who were boggled by that one
如果大家没有听明白这种表述
I'm going to say it again, in a different way.
我换个方式再讲一遍
Listen to one more alternative.
请听另一个版本
Let's define diag2.
我们定义DIAG2
These are named diag because
取名叫DIAG是因为
of Cantor's diagonal argument.
它来源于康托尔的对角论证法
These are instances of
这些事例最初都来自于
a famous argument which was originally used by
一个著名的论证
Cantor in the late part of the last century
也就是康托尔在19世纪末
to prove that the real numbers were not countable,
证明了实数是不可数的
that there are too many real numbers
整数与实数
to be counted by integers.
无法形成一一映射
That there are more points on a line,
数轴上的点
for example,
举例来说
than there are counting numbers.
比数轴上的刻度还要多
It may or may not be obvious,
这或许不是个显而易见的结论
and I don't want to get into that now.
但我不想深入讨论这个
But diag2
但是DIAG2
is again a procedure of one argument p.
也是一个参数为P的单参过程
It's almost the same as the previous one,
这几乎与之前的例子相同
which is, if it's safe to compute p on p,
如果计算(P P)是安全的
then I'm going to produce--
那么我就要
Oops, if
哦 漏了一个IF
then I want to compute
那么我就去计算
some other things
一些(P P)之外的东西
Otherwise I'm going to put out false.
否则我就返回FALSE
Where other then it says,
这里的OTHER-THAN意思是
whatever p of p,
不管这个(P P)是什么
I'm going to put out something else.
我都返回一些别的东西
I can give you an example of
我来给出一个
a definition of other than
OTHER-THAN的一个定义
which I think works.
我觉得它是可用的
Let's see.
来看看
Yes.
好
Where other than
定义OTHER-THAN
be a procedure of one argument x
参数为X的单参过程
which says,
过程体是
if its eq x to, say, quote a,
如果(EQ? X 'A)
then the answer is quote b.
那么结果是'B
Otherwise it's quote a.
否则结果是'A
That always produces something
这样无论参数是什么
which is not what its argument is.
返回值跟参数总是不相同的
That's all it is.
就是这样了
That's all I wanted.
这就是我要的
Well now let's consider this one,
我们考虑一下这个
diag2 of diag2.
(DIAG2 DIAG2)
Well look.
看
This only does something dangerous,
这个东西会做些危险的事情
like calling p of p,
比如求值(P P)
if it's safe to do so.
如果它是安全的
So if safe defined at all,
如果SAFE?能够被定义的话
if you can define such a procedure, safe,
如果你能定义SAFE?过程
then this procedure
那么这个过程
is always defined and therefore safe
也就顺理成章地是安全的
on any inputs.
对于任意输入来说都是
So diag2 of diag2
那么(DIAG2 DIAG2)
must reduce to other than diag2 of diag2.
就会返回(OTHER-THAN (DIAG2 DIAG2))
And that doesn't make sense,
这说不通
so we have a contradiction,
又产生了悖论
and therefore we can't define safe.
因此我们不能定义SAFE?
I just waned to do that twice,
我只想这样证明两次
slightly differently,
有些许不同
so you wouldn't feel
你不会感到
that the first one was a trick.
第一个证明是个把戏
They may be both tricks,
它们可能都是把戏
but they're at least slightly different.
但它们稍微有些不同
So I suppose that pretty much wraps it up.
因此 我想这就基本上讲清楚了
I've just proved what we call the halting theorem,
我们刚刚证明了所谓的“停机问题”
and I suppose with that we're going to halt.
我想 本课程也即将画上句号
I hope you have a good time.
希望你们有所收获
Are there any questions?
有什么问题吗?
Yes.
请讲
AUDIENCE: What is the value of s of diag1?
学生: (S DIAG1)的值是什么?
PROFESSOR: Of what?
教授: 什么的值?
AUDIENCE: S of diag1.
学生: (S DIAG1)的值
If you said s is a function, and then we can
如果你说S是个函数 我们就可以--
PROFESSOR: Oh, I don't know.
教授: 噢 我不知道啊
I don't know.
我不知道
It's a function,
它是一个函数
but I don't know how to compute it.
但我不知道如何计算它
I can't do it.
我做不到
I'm just a machine, too.
我也只是个机器
Right?
对吧?
And there's no machine
原则上来说
that in principle--
没有机器
it might be that in that particular case you just asked,
当然 也有可能会处在你刚才问的那个情况中
with some thinking I could figure it out.
花点时间还是可以计算出来
But in general
但通常情况下
I can't compute the value of s
我无法计算S的值
any better than any other machine can.
别的机器也做不到
There is such a function,
存在这样一个函数
it's just that no machine can be built to compute it.
没有任何机器能够计算它
Now
现在
there's a way of saying that that should not be surprising.
我这么来说也不会让你们吃惊
Going through this--
来想一想
I mean, I don't have time to do this here,
现在我没有时间给你们展示
but the number of functions is very large.
但这样的函数非常多
If there's a certain number of answers possible
如果有一定量的可能输入
and a certain number of inputs possible,
和一定量可能的结果
then it's the number of answers raised to the number inputs
那么结果数量的输入数量次幂
is the number of possible functions.
就是可能的函数的数量
On one variable.
这还是单参的函数
Now that's always bigger
而多参函数的个数
than the thing you're raising to,
又比这个幂次方
the exponent.
这个指数还要大
The number of functions is larger
函数的数量
than the number of programs
比一个人能写出的
that one can write,
程序的数量更多
by an infinity counting argument.
因为有无穷多的参数
And it's much larger.
可能会更多
So there must be a lot of functions
所以不可计算的函数数量
that can't be computed by programs.
一定会非常多
AUDIENCE: A few moments ago
学生：不久前
you were talking about specifications
你讲了规范
and automatic generation of solutions.
和自动生成解决方案
Do you see any steps
您觉得通过规范
between specifications and solutions?
能够生成解决方案么？
PROFESSOR: Steps between.
教授：“生成”
You mean, you're saying,
你是说
how you go about constructing
如何按照规范
devices given that have specifications for the device?
构建相应的装置吗?
AUDIENCE: There's a lot of software engineering
学生：软件工程中有很多
that goes through specifications through
层次化的设计
many layers of design and then implementation.
并进行实现的规范
PROFESSOR: Yes?
教授：是的
AUDIENCE: I was curious
学生：我很好奇
if you think that's realistic.
您觉得这现实吗?
PROFESSOR: Well I think that some of it's realistic
教授：我觉得其中一些是现实的
and some of it isn't.
另一些不现实
I mean, surely if I want to build an electrical filter
如果你想制造一个滤波器
and I have a rather interesting possibility.
我这有个挺有趣的例子
Supposing I want to build a thing that matches
假设我想制造一个东西
that matches some power output to the radio transmitter,
把无线电发射器的输出
to some antenna.
连接到某条天线上
And I'm really out of this power--
我先把它引出来
it's output tube out here.
这里是输出管线
And the problem is that they have different impedances.
问题是它们的阻抗不同
I want them to match the impedances.
我希望能够匹配阻抗
I also want to make a filter in there
我也想在其中加入一个滤波器
which is going to get rid of some harmonic radiation.
用来过滤一些谐波辐射
Well one old-fashioned technique for doing this is called
一种老派的技术叫作
image impedances, or something like that.
“影像阻抗”之类的东西
And what you do
你要做的是
is you say you have a basic module
你有个基础的模块
called an L-section.
称为L型滤波器
Looks like this.
就像这样
If I happen to connect this to some resistance, r,
如果把它连接到某些电阻R上
and if I make this impedance x, xl,
如果我把它的阻抗记作X_L
and if it happens to be q times r,
而它的值刚好又等于Q*R
then this produces a low pass filter
这就成了一个低通滤波器
with a q square plus one impedance match.
有Q^2+1的等效阻抗
Just what I need.
这就是我想要的
Because now I can take two of these,
因为这样我就可以
hook them together
把它们匹配到一起了
like this.
就像这样
OK, and I take another one
我拿来另一个
and I'll hook them together like that.
想这样把它们连到一起
And I have two L-sections hooked together.
有两个L型滤波器连接起来
And this will step the impedance down to one that I know,
这能让它的阻抗降到我知道的值
and this will step it up to one I know.
让它的阻抗升到我知道的值
Each of these is a low pass filter
这两个低通滤波器
getting rid of some harmonics.
都过滤掉了一些谐波
It's good filter,
这是个不错的滤波器
it's called a pie-section filter.
这就是π型滤波器
Great.
很好
Except for the fact that in doing what I just did,
除了实际上
I've made a terrible inefficiency in this system.
我在系统里放了些无用的东西
I've made two coils
我在本该只用一个的地方
where I should have made one.
用了两个线圈
And the problem with most software engineering art
在大多数软件工程技艺中
is that there's no mechanism,
在人工优化和编译之外
other than people optimization and compilers,
不存在一种机制
for getting rid of the redundant parts
能在自顶向下的设计中
that are constructed when doing top down design.
去掉冗余的部分
It's even worse,
或许会更糟
there are lots of very important structures
有很多重要的结构
that you can't construct at all this way.
你无法采用这种方式构建
So I think that the standard top down design
我觉得标准的自上而下的设计方式
is a rather shallow business.
是一种很短视的手段
Doesn't really capture
它不会真的抓到
what people want to do in design.
设计者真正想要的结果
I'll give you another electrical example.
我再举一个电子学的例子
Electrical examples are so much clearer
电子学的例子
than computational examples,
要比计算的例子直观得多
because computation examples require
因为计算的例子
a certain degree of complexity to explain them.
解释起来比较复杂
But one of my favorite examples
在电子学世界中
in the electrical world
我最喜欢的例子之一是
is how would I ever come up with the output stage
是如何设计中频放大器中
of this inter-stage connection in an IF amplifier.
输入级和输出级的连接方式
It's a little transistor here,
这是一个三极管
and let's see.
我们来看看
Well I'm going to have a tank,
这有个LC震荡电路
and I'm going to hook this up to, say,
我要把它
I'm going to link-couple that to the input of the next stage.
把它与下一级的输入线圈耦合在一起
Here's a perfectly plausible plan--
这是个完美的可行方案
well except for the fact that since I put that going up
除了我这个电流方向画错了
I should make that going that way. OK?
电流应该是这个方向
Here's a perfectly plausible plan for a--
这是个完美的可行方案
no I shouldn't.
不对
I'm dumb.
我犯蠢了
Excuse me.
对不起
Doesn't matter.
这不重要
The point is it's a perfect
关键在于这是一个
plan for a couple two stages together.
把两级耦合起来的完美方案
Now what the problem is what's this hierarchically?
分层来看时会产生什么问题?
It's not one thing.
它就不是同一个东西了
Hierarchically it doesn't make any sense at all.
当分层来看时它就没有任何意义了
It's the inductance of a tuned circuit,
这是一个调谐电路的电感
it's the primary of a transformer,
这是变压器的初级线圈
and it's also the DC path by
这是直流的通路
which bias conditions get to the
它是三极管的集电极
collector of that transistor.
的偏置条件
And there's no simple top-down design
没有任何简单的自顶向下设计
that's going to produce a structure like that
能够得到这样的结构
with so many overlapping uses for a particular thing.
对于同一个东西有大量的复用
Playing Scrabble,
玩拼字游戏
where you have to do triple word scores, or whatever,
当你要完成三倍分数的词时
is not so easy in top-down design strategy.
自顶向下的设计策略并不容易
Yet most of real engineering is based on
然而 大多数实际的工程学都是
on getting the most oomph for effort.
秉承着“尽其力而为之”
And that's what you're seeing here.
那就是你所看到的东西
Yeah?
嗯？
AUDIENCE: Is this the last question?
学生：这是最后一个问题吗?
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
PROFESSOR: Apparently so.
教授：看起来是
Thank you.
谢谢大家
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP
你所知道的有关计算的东西，其他人也都能学到。绝不要认为
似乎成功计算的钥匙就掌握在你的手里。你所掌握的，也是我认为
并希望的，也就是智慧：那种看到这一机器比你第一次站在它面前
时能做得更多的能力，这样你才能将它向前推进。
Alan J. Perlis (1922.4.1 - 1990.1.7)